# ARTHUR BAUVILLE Geoscientist & software developer

Yokohama, JP | +81 7041444511 | abauville@jamstec.go.jp | github| portfolio | publications

#### **SUMMARY**

Researcher with eleven years of experience in computational Earth Sciences, specialized in developing multiphysics simulation software and applying it to problems in geodynamics and structural geology. I am also a machine learning and data science practitioner (cf. my portfolio) with interest in deep learning and computer vision.

#### **SKILLS**

**Programming languages**: Python, C, MATLAB, Javascript, GLSL **Libraries**: PyTorch, OpenCV, Pandas, scikit-learn, scipy, openMP

Techniques: Finite elements, finite difference, HPC, computer vision, neural networks, data visualization,

supervised & unsupervised learning, Paraview (VTK)

## **EXPERIENCE**

## JAPAN AGENCY FOR MARINE-EARTH SCIENCES AND TECHNOLOGY - Yokohama, Japan

Researcher

Jul 2017 – Present

- External researcher

  Jan 2016 Jul 2017
- Developed a <u>simulation code</u> that utilizes the UNIX supercomputer cluster (C, Python, openMP, OpenGL)
- Performed data visualization, data analysis of simulation unstructured data (>1 TB)
- Advised researchers on statistical methods, machine learning and simulation
- Raised 120,000€ in academic grant to support academic research and student training
- Wrote and presented scientific publications and grants in international journals and conferences
- Organized a Germany-Japan joint collaboration which resulted in a Master thesis and a scientific publication

## **UNIVERSITY OF MAINZ – Mainz, Germany**

Post-doctoral researcher

Dec 2014 - Dec 2015

- Developed a program to speed up and improve the design of 3D numerical simulations
- Taught numerical simulation methods (Finite-element), geodynamics and machine learning. Level BSc., MSc.
- Used unsupervised learning (principal component analysis) to determine the origin of mantle rocks in Europe.

# UNIVERSITY OF LAUSANNE - Lausanne, Switzerland

Ph.D. student

Nov 2010 - Nov 2014

- Developed analytical and numerical models to explain formation of tectonic nappes in W. Switzerland
- Taught numerical simulation methods (Finite-element, finite-difference), machine learning, and field techniques (geological mapping, stereography, structural geology). Level BSc., MSc.
- Wrote international peer-reviewed articles, and presented results at conferences.
- Co-organized the conference GeoMod 2012 (~100 participants): arranged venues, design/maintained website

# **EDUCATION**

**UNIVERSITY OF LAUSANNE – Lausanne, Switzerland** 

Nov 2014

PhD in Earth Sciences

**UNIVERSITY OF GRENOBLE - Grenoble, France** 

Jun 2010

MSc. in Earth Sciences

**UNIVERSITY OF TOURS - Tours, France** 

Jun 2008

BSc. in Earth Sciences

#### ADDITIONAL

Languages: French, English, Japanese

Scientific publications: 16 peer-reviewed articles, ~200 citations

Machine learning competition: WAIDATATHON 2021, team leader, winner (1500\$).